<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most certaine and true relation of a strange monster or serpent found in the left ventricle of the heart of Iohn Pennant, Gentleman, of the age of 21. yeares. By Edward May Doctor of Philosophy and Physick, and professor elect of them, in the colledge of the academy of noble-men, called the Musæum Minervæ: physitian also extraordinary unto her most Sacred Majesty, Queene of great Brittany, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>May, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17709</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112479</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847729</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847729</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12788</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07320)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12788)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1027:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most certaine and true relation of a strange monster or serpent found in the left ventricle of the heart of Iohn Pennant, Gentleman, of the age of 21. yeares. By Edward May Doctor of Philosophy and Physick, and professor elect of them, in the colledge of the academy of noble-men, called the Musæum Minervæ: physitian also extraordinary unto her most Sacred Majesty, Queene of great Brittany, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>May, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p., folded plate : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Miller,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXXIX. [1639]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The "plate" is a woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medical parasitology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Heart --  Foreign bodies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Helminths --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12788:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12788:1"/>
            <p>A MOST CERTAINE AND TRVE RELATION OF A STRANGE MON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER OR SERPENT Found in the left Ventricle of the heart of IOHN PENNANT, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of the age of 21. yeares.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edward May</hi> Doctor of Philoſophy and Phyſick, and profeſſor Elect of them, in the Colledge of the Academy of Noble-men, called the Muſaeum Minervae: Phyſitian alſo extraordinary unto her moſt Sacred Majeſty, <hi>Queene of great Brittany,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>George Miller,</hi> MDCXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12788:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12788:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE LORD AND highly renowned Peere of this Kingdome, EDWARD Earle of Dorſet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Knight of the moſt Noble order of the garter, Lord High Chamberlaine unto her moſt Soveraigne Majeſty, QVEENE of <hi>great Brittane,</hi> &amp;c. And one of the Lords of his Majeſties moſt honourable privy Councell. <hi>Edward May</hi> wiſheth all health and glory.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR this Treatiſe I ſeeke no patronage, for if the Relation and the Author cannot defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, let them both ſuffer. A Swallow flies better then a Swanne, though his wing be leſſe: And one little Diamond will buy 17. of <pb facs="tcp:12788:3"/>thoſe ſtones that were drawne to <hi>S. Paules Church</hi> of 17. Tunnes: yet whether this Deſcription of mine be good, or great, worthy or otherwiſe, it is not dedicated to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as a matter preſuming towards your worth, or preſence, but as a publike obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the face of the world, of my future and more ſolid gratitude: You have honoured me before the Noble Peeres, and higheſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors of the Kingdome: You have otherwiſe done me reall favours, what am I, or what is in me that you have not conquered? and not by theſe benefits to me only, but theſe many yeares my obſervations of your moſt Noble nature, your more then humane partes, your vaſt and incredible comprehenſion of all things, both eſsentiall and accidentall to your place and dignity. Your innumerable merits and that univerſall acclamation of all men whatſoever, have made me, more your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervant then you know, and when after a ſhort ſpace God ſhall giue me to ſit a little qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, tending mine own affaires, your Lordſhip ſhall ſee, not by my writings but by my doings, that I am more your Lordſhips then any French or thrice devoted ſervant.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:12788:3"/>
            <head>A Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat my deſignes are in the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing</hi> of this Hiſtory, the Reader may finde every where in it, to be no other then the
<hi>Conſervation</hi> of the workes of God, and nature, and
<hi>preſervation</hi> of men: but for the <hi>Printing</hi> of it in Engliſh, I have neither end nor intent: For theſe two yeares it hath beene neglected by me, and peruſed up and downe in the hands of the beſt, and beſt learned, who have deſired ſatisfaction, touching ſo rare an oſtent: for the young Gentleman in whom it was found, deceaſed the 6<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. of
<hi>October,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord, 1637. My intention in this Deſcription was for the Continent, and not for our Ilands only, wherefore J ſtayed my hand till ſome oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to publiſh ſome other Lattine Treatiſes of mine owne with it; which many yeares have beene deſired: But now this being ſtill out of my hands, and licenſed for the preſſe before any notice given me; for the ſatisfaction of our own nation, and for the benefit of them who deſired the printing of it, I have freely given way to pleaſure any who ſhall deſire to read it: wherefore if <hi>Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onicall</hi> and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall Jdeas doe correſpond: and the readers honeſt mind anſwer my ſincere truth and good wiſhes, I have my end.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:12788:4"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>§. 1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Preface.</item>
               <item>§. 2. The History it ſelfe.</item>
               <item>§. 3. The Occaſion of this deſcription: and who were preſent.</item>
               <item>§. 4. How <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and the Ancients are to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, who ſaid that the heart was not ſubject to any diſeaſe: as alſo an enumeration of diſeaſes of the heart.</item>
               <item>§. 5. How ſuch Monſters are begotten or bred in the heart.</item>
               <item>§. 6. That theſe ſtrange generations are cauſed by the Temperament individuall.</item>
               <item>§. 7. What light and helpe men may have by ſuch relations, and ſuch reſolution of this difficulty as in the former Paragraph is ſet downe: and how that in latent cauſes ſome exteriour ſignature, or beames diſcover the diſeaſe.</item>
               <item>§ 8. That all creatures, things in the world, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes have their <hi>radij,</hi> as well as the Starres of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: prooved by <hi>Frier Bacon,</hi> and that moſt learned Philoſopher
<hi>Alkindus,</hi> and by reaſons and experience, and that there is no action but <hi>per radios,</hi> and that there is no action <hi>immediatione ſuppoſiti,</hi> but onely <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatione virtutis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. 9. How ſome Phiſitians have preſcribed againſt ſuch diſeaſes.</item>
               <item>§. 10. One reaſon why theſe occult maladies are ſo ſeldome found, and never cured: the many benefits of fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent diſſections.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 2. lin. 12. put in to. p. 4. l. 37. reade Caprizant, l. 38. open. p 13. l. 25. Aorts. p. 12. l. 16. yet. p. 19. l. 3. <hi>conventu concitiata.</hi> p 27. l. 25 <hi>Kirannides.</hi> p. 28. l. 7. diſcovered.
32. l. 14. <hi>Regulus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>atus</hi> l. 21. <hi>eſſentiator.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <pb facs="tcp:12788:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of heart with parasitic worm</figDesc>
               </figure> 
               <pb facs="tcp:12788:5"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of parasitic worm</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>That the 7. of <hi>October,</hi> this 1637 an <hi>Embrion</hi> of this forme and dimentions, as is here deſcribed was found in the left Ventricle of the heart of <hi>Iohn Pennant</hi> Gentleman, of the age of 21. yeares, or thereabouts, Wee who ſaw it teſtifie under our hands:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward May</hi> Doctor of Phyſick.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iacob Heydon</hi> Surgeon.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Elizabeth Herris</hi> Aunt unto the ſaid <hi>Iohn Pennant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dorothy Pennant</hi> Mother to the ſaid <hi>Iohn Pennant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Berry.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>.
<hi>Gentlemans</hi> marke. This is my wives marke I teſtify. <hi>George Gentleman.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> 
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12788:5"/>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR <hi>THEODORE MAIHERNE</hi> KNIGHT, CHIEFE PHY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SITIAN UNTO HIS MOST Soveraigne Majeſty, KING <hi>of great Brittany,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Edward May</hi> wiſheth all health.</head>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <head>§. I.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong thoſe many favours you have afforded me, your private, ſweet, moſt familiar and long Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies with me have been ſingular: While you lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide important af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, out of an admirable candour and love to Learning, (in which few excell you) vouchſafe ſometimes to treate with me <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12788:6"/>concerning occult <hi>Philoſophy</hi> and moſt ſacred medicines: In one of which meetings, as I had laid open what I had found in the <hi>Sini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Ventricle</hi> of the heart of a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which you deſired me to deſcribe while the <hi>Species</hi> were yet freſh in my memory, as others many both Phyſitians and Friends have done alſo: So here I have done it: And do firſt communicate it unto your ſelfe, as a ſmall <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of my certaine knowledge of your great and admirable perfections in many Sciences, nececeſſary him who is Phyſitian to Princes; and of my ſingular eſtimation of them: As alſo to ſow ſome ſeeds of future Diſcourſes, both new and worthy of that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and divine Magick which we both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe: Well knowing that good uſe may bee made of this Hiſtory by all Phyſitians, and profit unto many, as I have partly declared in the Subſequents.</p>
            <p>It is an oſtent and prodigy, ſtrange and incredible which J am to paint: And if in many Phyſitians of beſt eſteeme, and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity I had not found Relations very like it, mine owne heart would not have given credit to mine owne eyes and hands when firſt I found it: But you have found one like it in the heart of a Noble Lord; but when you have ſeen this, I ſhall know whether ſo grown, or of this forme, or otherwiſe: Let the Vulgar and Ignorant, beleeve it, or not believe it, Phyſitians and knowing men (as you do) will <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12788:6"/>receive it: And therefore briefly the certaine Hiſtory and true Relation is this.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>§. 2.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſeventh of <hi>October</hi> this yeare cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, 1637 the Lady <hi>Herris</hi> wife un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sir <hi>Francis Herris</hi> Knight, came unto me and deſired that I would bring a <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon</hi> with me, to diſſect the body of her Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew <hi>Iohn Pennant,</hi> the night before decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to ſatisfie his friends concerning the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his long ſickneſſe and of his death: And that his mother, to whom my ſelfe had once or twice given helpe ſome yeares before concerning the Stone, might be aſcertained whether her Sonne died of the Stone or no? Upon which intreaty I ſent for Maſter
<hi>Iacob Heydon Surgeon,</hi> dwelling againſt the <hi>Caſtle Taverne</hi> behind S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Clements Church</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> who with his Man-Servant came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me: And in a word we went to the houſe and Chamber where the dead man lay: We diſſected the naturall Region and found the bladder of the young man full of purulent and ulcerous matter: The upper parts of it bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and all of it rotten: The right kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney quite conſumed, the left tumified as big as any two kidnies, and full of ſanious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: All the inward and carnoſe parts eaten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way &amp; nothing remaining but exteriour skins.</p>
            <p>No where did we find in his body either <pb n="4" facs="tcp:12788:7"/>Stone or gravell. The Spleen and Liver not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in any diſcernable degree, only part of the Liver was growne unto the Coſtall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes, by reaſon of his writing profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Wee aſcending to the Vitall Region, found the Lungs reaſonable good, the heart more globoſe and dilated, then long; the right Ventricle of an aſhe colour ſhrivelled, and wrinkled like a leather purſe without money, and not any thing at all in it: the <hi>Pericardium,</hi> and Nervous Membrane, which conteyneth that illuſtrious liquour of the Lungs, in which the heart doth bath its ſelfe, was quite dried alſo: The left Ventricle of the heart, being felt by the Surgions hand, appeared to him to be as hard as a ſtone, and much greater then the right: which upon the firſt ſight gave us ſome cauſe of wonder, ſeeing (as you know) the right Ventricle is much greater then the left: Wherefore I wiſhed M. <hi>Heydon</hi> to make inciſion, upon which iſſued out a very great quantity of blood; and to ſpeake the whole verity, all the blood that was in his body left, was gathered to the left Ventricle, and contayned in it<note n="*" place="margin">Here thoſe men may be handſomely queſtioned (who ſay that the pulſe is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the impulſe, of blood into the Arteryes or the Syſtole of the heart) what was become of the pulſe in this man all the while that the whole blood betooke it ſelfe into the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art, here was either a living man without pulſe, or pulſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Syſtole of the heart. For what could the arteryes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive where nothing was to be received? or how could there be pulſe where was no impulſe into the arteryes? The pulſe the doubtleſſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s from another cauſe, and is a farre other matter then moſt men conceive: for there are in a ſound man
4450 pulſations in an houre, in a ſicke man ſometimes in ſome percute fevers and diſeaſes above 35600, and more, which cannot be from ſo many ſeverall expreſſions and receptions of blood; for it is impoſſible the heart ſhould make compreſſion, and the arteryes apartion, ſo often in that ſpace. Nay in <hi>Dicrot: Capizant.</hi> and other inordinate pulſes, diverſe pulſes ſtrike in leſſe ſpace then the mouth of an arterey can goe, much more then in leſſe times then it can open, ſhut, and open againe, which 3. acts are requiſite to the beginning of a ſecond pulſe. But of this I have largely treated in my 3, Booke <hi>De Febribus.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12788:7"/>No ſooner was that Ventricle emptied, but M.
<hi>Heydon</hi> ſtill complaining of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and hardneſſe of the ſame, my ſelfe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to neglect his words, becauſe the left Ventricle is thrice as thicke of fleſh as the right is in ſound men for conſervation of Vitall Spirits; I directed him to an other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition: but he keeping his hand ſtill upon the heart, would not leave it, but ſaid againe that it was of a ſtrange greatneſſe and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; whereupon I deſired him to cut the Orifice wider: by which meanes we preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceived a carnouſe ſubſtance, as it ſeemed to us wreathed together in foldes like a worme or Serpent, the ſelfe ſame forme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the firſt <hi>Iconography:</hi> at which we both much wondred, and I intreated him to ſeperate it from the heart, which he did, and wee carryed it from the body to the window, and there layed it out, in thoſe juſt dimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are here expreſſed in the ſecond figure.</p>
            <p>The body was white of the very colour of the whiteſt skin of mans body: but the skin was bright and ſhining, as if it had beene var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed over; the head all bloody, and ſo like the head of a Serpent, that the Lady
<hi>Herris</hi> then ſhivered to ſee it, and ſince hath often ſpoken it, that ſhe was inwardly troubled at it, becauſe the head of it was ſo truely like the head of a Snake.</p>
            <p>The thighes and branches were of fleſh <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12788:8"/>colour, as alſo all theſe fibraes, ſtrings, nerves, or whatſoever elſe they were.</p>
            <p>After much contemplation and conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures what ſtrange thing that part of the heart had brought forth unto us, I reſolved to try the certainty, and to make full explora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both for mine owne experience and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, as alſo to give true teſtimony to others that ſhould heare of it: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I ſearched all parts of it, to finde whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were a pituitoſe and bloody Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, or the like: Or a true organicall body, and Conception: J firſt ſearched the head and found it of a thicke ſubſtance, bloody and glandulous about the necke, ſomewhat broken, (as J conceived) by a ſudden or violent ſeparation of it from the heart, which yet ſeemed to me to come from it eaſily enough.</p>
            <p>The body I ſearched likewiſe with a bodkin betweene the Leggs or Thighs, and I found it perforate, or hollow, and a ſolid body, to the very length of a ſilver bodkin, as is here deſcribed: At which the Spectators wondered. And as not credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me, ſome of them tooke the bodkin after me, made triall themſelves, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſatisfied, that there was a gut, Veine or Artery, or ſome ſuch Analogicall thing that was to ſerve that Monſter for uſes naturall: Amongſt whom the Lady <hi>Herris</hi> and the Surgian made tryall after me with <pb n="7" facs="tcp:12788:8"/>their owne hands, and have given their hands that this Relation is true. This La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy dwelleth at the ſigne of the Sugar loafe in S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſtreet in the <hi>Convent Garden.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <head>§. 3.</head>
            <p>THis ſtrange and monſtrous Embryon borne in the ſaid Ventricle, which as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaith is nouriſhed neither with meats nor drinkes, <hi>Sed purâ &amp; illuſtri ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia,</hi> taking aliment from the blood puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied out of the next Ciſterne; made mee (importuned with other occaſions then) to leave this new and rare Spectacle in the charge of the Surgion, who had a great deſire to conſerve it, had not the Mother deſired that it ſhould be buried where it was borne; ſaying and repeating, <hi>As it came with him, ſo it ſhall goe with him:</hi> Wherefore the Mother ſtaying in the place departed not till ſhee had ſeene him ſow it up againe into the body after my going away.</p>
            <p>Which as ſoone as I heard, I preſently deſcribed the forme of it at home, <hi>inter rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ora à me reperta:</hi> And thus this Hiſtory had alwayes beene buried from the World, (the Mother having thus buried the Creature) if your ſelfe and others had not deſired a figure and narration of it, which cauſed me to take the hands, and mindes of ſome of them who <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12788:9"/>were preſent: Who being neareſt the young man, were moſt likely to ſay the beſt, and therefore being beſides people of good fame and reputation might bee credited; conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that they would ſay nothing at all ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt their owne houſe, or againſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity more then what apparent and cleare truth ſhould neceſſitate them unto: Which from themſelves and under their hands, here I have done.</p>
            <p>There were alſo divers others, ſuch as dwelled in the houſe, and ſome that came in, who beheld it, after whom I have no leiſure to enquire: But ſuch who will ſcarce believe their Creed, or any true mans word, or that men have ſenſes (which have alwaies beene reputed incorrupted Witneſſes,) may goe into the high buildings upon the Street in Saint
<hi>Giles</hi> Pariſh, and at the corner houſe next the greene Dragon where the Young-man died; they may make further inquiſition.</p>
            <p>Since which time the Mother hath remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her ſelfe into
<hi>Bloomesbury</hi> neare unto the houſe of one Maſter <hi>Nurſe,</hi> who directed me to her lodgings; a man well knowne in all that Region.</p>
            <p>Miſtris <hi>Gentleman</hi> dwelleth neare unto S. <hi>Clements Church</hi> in the Strand, and the Chirurgion, or his man can direct them to the houſe.</p>
            <p>Moreover that day all of us that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <pb n="9" facs="tcp:12788:9"/>at this ſight related to our friends, wives, or husbands what we had found, as they will teſtifie.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory therefore being verified by as much teſtimony as humane perſwaſion need require: Except nothing but oath will content ſome, which if it ſhall be found neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Authority: It will moſt readily come forth alſo and obey: It is moſt requiſite that ſomething be ſaid of this or any ſuch like matters generated in mans heart, both for the manner of their generation and the way of their cure, and by what means ſuch rare and incredible cauſes of death may bee found out in time and taken away.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <head>§. 4.</head>
            <p>SUch matters as theſe were worthy of your ſelfe, and a man of your long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Yet becauſe this ſtrange generation was found by me, I will conſult with your learning, rather then by any haſty reſolution, determine and diſcourſe a little to ſtate a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of no ſmal difficulty;
<note place="margin">Hip de morbis Avicen l. 3. ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 11.</note>ſince <hi>Hippocrates</hi> firſt hath given the occaſion, which was this; <hi>Cor nullo morbo laborat:</hi> the heart laboureth of no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe: &amp; Prince <hi>Avicen, cor longinquum anocumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> the heart is farr remote from dangers. And yet contrary to theſe: Very many Phyſitians enumerate theſe diſeaſes of the heart; the <hi>Maraſmus, Syncope,</hi> the <hi>Cordiack</hi> paſſion <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12788:10"/>
               <hi>Lypothymy, Apostems, Vlcers, Botheralia, Corroſion</hi> of <hi>Sublimate;</hi> and I dare adde, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes which afflict the heart by reaſon of diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations from the head in ſome who have had the unction: Tremors alſo and palpitations of the heart; as
<hi>Peter Ebanus</hi> in his Booke <hi>de Venenis:</hi> And the
<hi>Paralyſis</hi> of the heart, as old <hi>Aurelianus</hi> in his ſecond Booke of <hi>Slow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsions:</hi> After <hi>Haerophylus</hi> and
<hi>Eraſistratus</hi> have obſerved.</p>
            <p>And now of late <hi>Skinkius</hi> and others have found wormes in
<hi>Cordis capſulâ,</hi> which is the <hi>Pericardium:</hi> But I ſpeake more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely and punctually, that now in the left Ventricle of the heart, this Worme or Serpent hath beene found: Which the Mother of the Young-man ſaith, was at leaſt of three yeares growth, for ſo long he complained of his breaſt, and as ſhee ſaith would never button his Doublet in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but be open breaſted in all weathers, till he had waſhed his hands and face, and was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to palpitations.</p>
            <p>Now then that wee may judge whether <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and
<hi>Avicen</hi> direct their ſpeeches: theſe reaſons are to be admitted.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>1</label> Firſt, from the ſituation of the heart, <hi>in medio medij pectoris,</hi> ſaith <hi>Avicen,</hi> in the middle of the middle of the breſt: which Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematically is not true: for ſo the baſis or upper part, or <hi>caput</hi> onely is placed in an Equidiſtance from the <hi>diaphragma</hi> (the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12788:10"/>
               <hi>furcula,</hi>) and the <hi>Clanicula,</hi> (and the <hi>furcula ſuperior</hi>) and betweene the <hi>Vertebra</hi> of the backe and the
<hi>anterior Sternon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>2</label> The Second is, that the heart dwelleth in a ſtrong pannicle, and ſuch an one, that <hi>non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venitur panniculus compar ei in ſpiſsitudine, ut ſit ei Clypeus &amp; tutamen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hip. l. de Cord.</note> that no pannicle is comparable unto it, that it may be a ſhield and defence unto the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">reason </seg>3</label> Thirdly, <hi>Avicen</hi> addeth, that the heart it ſelfe is created of ſtrong fleſh, that it may be
<hi>longinquum anocumentis, in quo contextae ſunt ſpecies villarum fortium:</hi> Diverſe ſtrong ſtrings admirably woven together do bind and ſtrengthen the heart, and give it aptitude for motion, and reſiſtance.
<hi>Hippocrates</hi> long before <hi>Avicen</hi> ſaith the ſame, and things of greater conſequence: <hi>Cor eſt muſculus fortis, &amp;c.</hi> The heart is a ſtrong muſcle, <hi>non nervo, ſed denſitate carnis &amp; conſtrictione:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hip. ubi ſupra.</note> not by his nervous nature, but by ſolidity of fleſh and conſtriction: And in the heart there lye hidden diverſe skins like ſpiders webs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, which do ſo bind and ſhut the endes of the forts, that no man ignorant, knowes how to take out the heart, but will take up one for an other. Neither can water or wind pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate into the heart: and more; <hi>Cor tuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam habet circumdatam, &amp; est in ipſâ humor modicus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Vt cor ſanum in cuſtodiâ floreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eat: habet autem humiditatem tantam quanta ſat is eſt aeſtuanti in medelam: hunc humorem cor <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12788:11"/>emungit bibendo ipſum aſſumens &amp; conſumens, pulmonis nimiram potum lambens:</hi> He ſpeakes further of the cover called the <hi>Epiglottis,</hi> that nothing may enter that way but what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient; So that ſeeing the heart is fortified with ſuch ſtrength of ribbs, with ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſuch skins, ſuch fortitude of ſubſtance, ſuch denſity of fleſh, ſuch excellence of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quour, ſuch curious filaments, that nothing can enter, hurt, or come neere the heart to make it ſicke: but that it is able to defend it ſelfe, both by its owne ſituation, ſtrength, and happy condition in very many reſpects, and keepe out or put backe whatſoever alſo by force ſhall come neere unto it: It remaineth that the heart is not, neither can be ſubject to any diſeaſe, or at leaſt not eaſily.</p>
            <p>Yea thoſe other men who enumerate the diſeaſes of the heart; grant, as chiefely <hi>Valeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus de Tharanta</hi> and the <hi>Arabians</hi> all confeſſe that a <hi>Syncope</hi> hapneth, or elſe death as ſoone as any diſeaſe approacheth, or hurt toucheth the ſubſtance of the heart; alſo <hi>Avicen, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus de Ebano</hi> relate that the forementi-oned diſeaſes kill as ſoone as any of them touch the ſubſtance of the heart: So alſo <hi>Herophylus</hi> coefeſſed that ſudden death followed if a <hi>Paralyſis</hi> once ſurprized the heart: And for <hi>Bothors</hi> or <hi>Phlegmo's,</hi> or <hi>Eriſipelas</hi> or the like, they ſay that they are diſeaſes of the heart <hi>initiativè</hi> only, and not
<hi>ſubjectivè,</hi> to dwell there any time.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12788:11"/>And indeed I am fully perſwaded that the heart ſuffereth a <hi>maraſmus privativè,</hi> by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of due tranſmiſſion from other parts, rather then that <hi>marcor</hi> ſhould follow <hi>àd cordis ſubſtantiae ariditatem;</hi> for if any part have good ſubſtance in it, the heart hath; and therefore
<hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaith, that <hi>quando fontes reſiccati fuerint homo moritur:</hi> that the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricles have the laſt humidity in them: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Galen</hi> ſeemeth to deſert his Maſter in ſaying, <hi>a cordis ariditate incipere malum.</hi> Viz, <hi>veram ſenectutem &amp; interitum naturalem.</hi> Whereas hee ſhould have ſaid the contrary: that the aridity of the heart followeth the deſiccation and want of due tranſmiſſion of other parts: Yee if J may ſpeake my mind freely, <hi>Hippocrates</hi> is not to be taken ſimply, that the heart cannot be any wayes affected; but perhaps in the ſenſe of <hi>Galen,</hi> that the heart ſuffereth little or no paine by reaſon the ſubſtance of the heart hath but little ſenſation, having but one little nerve for feeling from the ſixt Conjugation, and that is ſomewhat obſcure alſo.<note place="margin">Gal. 2. pla. 8.</note> Or if hee meane, as indeed I am ſure hee doth, that diſeaſes doe not affect the heart; hee is to bee underſtood that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily they doe not, but very ſeldome, by reaſon of the carnous parts, <hi>Cor ſolidum ac denſum ut ab humore non aegrotet, &amp; prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea nullus morbus in corde aboritur, caput autem &amp; Splen maximè ſunt morbis ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxia,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:12788:12"/>His ſpeech is evidently comparative; elſe wee ſee very often that which hee never ſaw in all his long life and experience: And indeed we ſee now very frequently the heart affected with Impoſthumes, with Wormes, with Abſceſſes, with Fleamy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion both in the Eares of the heart and Ventricles, yea and now with a Serpent: And yet men live divers yeares with them, and many other diſeaſes both <hi>per eſſentiam &amp; Conſenſum,</hi> all kinde of diſtempers both equall and unequall, of which the Ancients have left no memory nor mention unto us, with which the Books of late Phyſitians are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate. Wherefore the propoſitions of the Ancient Phyſitians muſt have a friendly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation; or elſe mens hearts now a daies are more paſſible and obnoxious unto diſeaſes then in former ages, which by me as yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily be admitted: Wee are forced therefore to conclude that the heart <hi>per eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam &amp; primariò &amp; ſubjectivè</hi> may be afflicted with a diſeaſe and cauſe of death, and it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe be conceived, ſeeing ſuch crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are begotten in it; yet doubtles exteriour diſeaſes kill ſooner then innate.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <head>§. 5.</head>
            <p>BUt this then begets a greater queſtion, how this Monſter or ſuch as this ſhould bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten or bred in the heart, ſo defended, as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12788:12"/>hath beene ſaid, more then all the body, and in the moſt defended part of the heart, the left Ventricle three times thicker of fleſh and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance then the right? as alſo of what matter? ſeeing that Cell is poſſeſſed and repleniſhed with the beſt, pureſt and moſt illuſtrious liquor in the body, the blood Arteriall and the vitall ſpirits.</p>
            <p>There are who conceive that pervious paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages may be found for little Wormes and the like to enter into the heart: but they muſt give a better way then any that J have yet ſeene doe, as alſo the Wormes muſt be very little. Others ſay, that ſuch matters are cauſed by the ill habit of the heart; by which if they meane the ſubſtance of the heart, it is not to be receaved, till the heart hath beene hurt by ill diſtributions and tranſmiſſions which in our caſe is otherwiſe: for halfe of the heart, the left Ventricle, (the <hi>Matrix</hi> of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent) was ſolid and ſtill good: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not in the ill habit of the ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Others thinke that thoſe Wormes which create ſometimes the
<hi>mal della luna,</hi> as the <hi>Italians</hi> terme it, living in the
<hi>pericardium,</hi> and gnawing the heart: Of which there are innumerable Stories.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heben flreit lib de peſte telleth us one, of a Prince to whoſe heart a white Worme was found cleaving with a ſharp and horny noſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexius pedemont anus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Sceret.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12788:13"/>telleth us of an other:</hi> and ſo <hi>Math: Corvar: lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 28. <hi>Conſult. med.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Stowe's <hi>Cronnicle ad annum</hi> 1586. <hi>of Q</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>a matter of this nature, in an Horſe is recorded as a memorable thing in theſe wordes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Seventeenth day of March, a ſtrange thing hapned, the like whereof before hath not beene heard of in our time. Master</hi> Dorington
<hi>of</hi> Spaldwick <hi>in the County of</hi> Huntington <hi>Eſquire, one of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Gentlemen Pentioners, had an horſe which died ſuddenly, and being ripped to ſee the cauſe of his death, there was found in the hole of the heart of the ſame horſe, a Worme which lay on a round heape in a kall or skinn, of the likeneſſe of a Toade; which being taken out and ſpread abroad, was in forme and faſhion not eaſie to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: The length of which worme divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into many graines to the number of fifty (ſpred from the body like the branches of a Tree) was from the ſnout to the end of the longeſt graine ſeventeene inches, having ſoure iſſues in the graines from which drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped forth a red water: The body in big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe round about was three inches and a halfe, the colour whereof was very like a Mackerel. This monſtrous worme found in manner aforeſaid, crawling to have got away, was ſtabbed in with a dagger and died; which being dryed was ſhewed to <pb n="17" facs="tcp:12788:13"/>many honourable perſonages of this Realme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this <hi>Horſe-worme</hi> or <hi>Serpent</hi> be Chronicled, how much more may this be memorized for Poſterity? Or that which you have, or that which you told me was found in the heart of the Lord <hi>Boclew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By reaſon theſe were found in Men, that in an Horſe: and this found by me of greater length, and more certaine forme, then that which they could not tell how to deſcribe.</p>
            <p>As alſo thoſe peeces of black fleſh genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the left Ventricle, of which <hi>Benivenius</hi> hiſtorizeth one, <hi>C.</hi> 35.
<hi>de abdit is,</hi> in forme of a Medler, upon the Artery; and
<hi>Veſalius, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>de humani corporis fabricâ,</hi> ſpeaketh of a moſt Noble and learned Perſonage, in the left Ventricle of whoſe heart, two pounds of blacke glandulous fleſh were found; the heart extended like a pregnant wombe.</p>
            <p>Yea and thoſe <hi>pituitoſe</hi> carnoſities and other matters, ſo often ſeene in the left Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle, by <hi>Neretus Neretius</hi> that famous Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian of <hi>Florence,</hi> and <hi>Eraſtus, part.</hi> 5. <hi>diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. de feb, putrid:</hi> may be generated in the
<hi>pericardium,</hi> either by drinkes of ill condition ſliding into the
<hi>Trachaea,</hi> and ſo into the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, and the heart:
<note place="margin">Cornelius Gemmad de Naturae divinis characteriſmis:</note> and ſometimes ſome ſmall ſeedes or attomes of creeping creatures; which <hi>Cornelius Gemma</hi> ſetteth forth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12788:14"/>and hiſtoriſeth many ſtrange matters in this kinde, as ſome to vomit <hi>Yeeles</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents</hi> of ſtrange formes: and it is a common ſaying of the <hi>Pedemontanes,</hi> and ſuch as drinke the waters of the <hi>Alpes;</hi> that every ſuch man borne hath a Frog to his brother. Such things may paſſe into the ſtomak, but rarely into the heart.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <head>§. 6.</head>
            <p>BUt that which I have to ſay, is this; that theſe ſtrange and extraordinary genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are cauſed from the temperament indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall, for you well know that there is a double temperament; the one Specificall, the other individuall; the one is <hi>fixum</hi> and unalterable, the other is
<hi>temperamentum fluxum,</hi> and accidentall.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Specificall</hi> temperament, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the vitall acts ceaſe, yet the <hi>ſpecificall</hi> act is never changed; for you ſee that the parts of this or that animall, retaine their
<hi>ſpecificall</hi> vertue when they are dead: as herbes, or thoſe partes of herbes, as leave, ſeedes or rootes, keepe their property, and retaine their owne heates or ſavours, when they are cut away, or taken up from the ground: Yea and there are certaine ſpecifike atoms which alwayes continue after putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and extreame drineſſe in the fixed ſalt.</p>
            <q> 
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12788:14"/>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Lucret. lib. 1.</note>Sunt igitur ſolida primordia ſimplicitate</l>
               <l>Quae minimis ſtipata cohaerent partibus arte</l>
               <l>Non ex ullorum conventa conciliatu</l>
               <l>Sed magis aeterna pollentia ſimplicitate</l>
               <l>Vnde ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> avelli quicquam ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diminui jam</l>
               <l>Concedit natura reſervans ſemina rebus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This temperament is proper to every creature: for Man hath his temperament, the Lyon his, hyſopp his, and the roſe his owne: For God made every thing, <hi>ſecundum ſpecies ſuas, &amp; in genere ſuo producat aqua in ſpecies ſuas, &amp; omne volatile ſecundum genus ſuum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et Deus fecit beſtias juxta ſpecies ſuas &amp; omne reptile terrae in genere ſuo, &amp; producat terra animamin genere ſuo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherfore the Specificall temperament of <hi>Socrates</hi> doth not differ from the temperament of <hi>Hippocrates, Plato, Cato,</hi> or any other man: which may be well put againſt <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who thought the ſoules of men did differ in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility one from an other: which difference can no way be founded upon the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpecifically, but rather upon the jndi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall, which is but the accidentall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Individualls of the ſame <hi>ſpecies;</hi> which followeth ſome peculiar determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of th' horoſcopant; or elſe upon ſome other ſpeciall helpe, or hinderance; as from the ſingular ſcite of Heaven, aſcention of Starres, aſpect in flux, the aliment of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, either more or leſſe elaborate; and <pb n="20" facs="tcp:12788:15"/>many other matters every creature borne hath according to the felicity or infelicity of his generation: eſpecially Man, who of all other creatures is nouriſhed with moſt variety of meates and drinkes: We alſo ſee every day that ſuch men are more hot, and vivacious, who are borne either in the Starres of <hi>Leo,</hi> or the Sun
<hi>Orientiall:</hi> they alſo to be of more ſuculent habit, who are born within the ſecond <hi>quadrate</hi> of the Moon: and ſuch to be leaſt vital, who are born in the ſilence of the Moon, herbs alſo gathered the Moon, decreaſing, have leſſe force: &amp; the very ſoile often doth either ſo aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ordwarfe plants, and herbes, and give them ſuch ſtrange conditions, that they are found degenerat, and ſcarcely the ſame herbs: As for the prolifick matter, it breedes (as Phyſitions ſay) a male, or female, as it is more or leſſe concocted: There are alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe conjunct matters, which helpe or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der generation, as ſuch matter doth which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth much <hi>a punctis ſpecificis,</hi> or <hi>à ſemine,</hi> for the <hi>ſperma</hi> may be much, which is <hi>materia augment ativa,</hi> but the ſeed is ſo little of which a giant is generated, that as <hi>novum lumen</hi> ſaith: it can be no greater at firſt moment of conception, then in proportion to the 8200. part of a graine of wheate; which confirmeth that of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that the fortieth day after conception, <hi>homo formicá non major;</hi> from which augmentative matter it is (which is made of various and alterative aliment) that <pb n="21" facs="tcp:12788:15"/>children differ ſo much from both their owne parents: hence one ſweates and ſweares at the ſight of a Cat: and an other forſakes the table at the ſight of a Pigg or Gooſe; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of which antipathies and diverſities, are founded in the latent matter ſpermatike, as if the Mother of one, ſomewhat before her Sonne was begotten, had eaten a mouſe; and the other fed upon the eares of a Jew.</p>
            <p>All which is ſaid to illuſtrate, that there is in many men, a certaine connate matter and obedientall, ſuſceptible of divers diſeaſes, and infelicities: Wherefore it was not ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, as worthily ſaid; <hi>Foeliciſsimum eſt benè naſci,</hi> it is a moſt happy thing to be well borne.</p>
            <p>And from this <hi>Diatheſes</hi> and ill diſpoſitions may many a ſtrange ſickneſſe in after ages ſpring, as time, diet and other accidents doe alter or intend the heat, cold, or acrimony of the humour and blood, or ſome other qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>I pray <hi>Sir,</hi> note well the faithfull Relation of a moſt underſtanding and ſincere man, M. <hi>Iohn Whiſtler,</hi> one of the Benchers of <hi>Graies-Inn</hi> and Recorder of <hi>Oxford,</hi> who upon my Narration of this Hiſtory of <hi>Iohn Pennant</hi> (the very ſame day, or the next that I found the Serpent;) told me that in his youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger daies himſelfe was a great Cock-Maſter, and one of his old fighting Cocks beginning to droope, he thought it beſt to cut off his <pb n="22" facs="tcp:12788:16"/>head, which as ſoone as it was done, there appeared and ſhot out betweene the skinns another head and neck, like that of his Cock, but it was a kinde of gelly (as hee conceived) with a very fine skin upon it, with a bill and a little combe: The reſt was not ſearched, which perhaps was bred of ſome Egg in the body of the Cock, which kind of Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are very rare, yet the ſacred <hi>Scripture</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention of <hi>Cockatrices:</hi> Which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe cannot be bred but of ſome humour or blood exalted to ſome extraordinary and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternaturall degree of heat, cold, or ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or ſome other quality: Which firſt the naturall heat and valour of that bird proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth: Secondly his martiall profeſſion and terrible battells performed almoſt to death, all his life long; as alſo being begotten of ſuch like Anceſtors, himſelfe alſo excelling in heat and fiery ſpirits accidentall.</p>
            <p>Compare this Young-mans ſtate alſo with this hiſtory; his right kidny wholy conſumed, his left tumified as big as any two kidnies or three, full of ulcerous matter: So likewiſe his bladder full of ulcer, and rottenneſſe, and nothing in his body to be found the cauſe of this: Wherefore the ſharpneſſe and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary heate of the blood or ſome ſuch like quality was the cauſe of the Ulcers, and ſo alſo conſequently of that extraordinary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction in the heart: For nothing els appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth whatſoever may be conceived: And this <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12788:16"/>accidentall temperament of the blood, I take to be the cauſe of this which we found in the heart: For in the heart (if any where) was the greateſt heat, and if in any part of the heart in the left Ventricle, the principall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle of arteriall blood and ſpirits: And I have more to confirme me in this opinion, having certaine knowledge both of the diet of his Mother and Grand-mother alſo, and of his owne: Which I am not willing to make publique; but to make private uſe of it to my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>All which ſhall not by me bee intended to prejudice any other better judgement concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning other like conceits; by reaſon that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages to that Ventricle may be ſometimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, although very rarely: But to informe you of ſome peculiar knowledge that I have of this mans Hiſtory; which may give us great light concerning others of like condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>I could here diſcourſe how the imagination produceth ſtrange things in men; and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not only in our owne bodies, but alſo <hi>in hyle mundi,</hi> as <hi>Fryer Bacon</hi> prooveth,<note place="margin">Ro. Bacon. l. de Coelo &amp; mundo</note> and Prince <hi>Avicen:</hi> But this I will not attempt, except you ſhall judge this Relation may be beneficiall to any, and then I ſhall diſcuſſe it out at large.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:12788:17"/>
            <head>§. 7.</head>
            <p>BUt to me the reſolution of this matter ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth very profitable to know how theſe things may be bred in men, for I ſuppoſe, men from hence will take ſpeciall care to alter the accidentall temperament of humors, if they find them excell in any high degree of heate, cold, ſharpnes, or the like, ſuch as have in them inconvenience and danger, and to deale with learned Phyſitians in time.</p>
            <p>So alſo is the knowledge of ſingular uſe and benefit to know when men are affected with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch diſeaſe, and how they may be cured.</p>
            <p>As for the knowledge of abſtruſe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret affections, where perhaps no dolor gives certitude of the place affected, as in diſeaſes by conſent, when ſome other parts are more afflicted, ſuch skill is worthy of a Phyſitian, and at any rate to be procured: But how or where ſhall we have it? Who writeth of it? Who hath ſo much as ever dreamed of any ſuch helpe to mankind? For mine owne part I never yet read of any <hi>Signa pathognomonica</hi> of any ſuch diſeaſe: Neither doe I know where to find one graine of inſtruction in this, as alſo in divers other diſeaſes (which I can nominate) more then from mine owne obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and care. Wherefore if I ſet downe one thing which is not common nor els where to be found. I hope you will take it as my good <pb n="25" facs="tcp:12788:17"/>wiſh unto the
<hi>Common-wealth</hi> of Phyſitians, and I will lay my ground upon two Hiſtories of mine own: the one was in <hi>December, anno.</hi> 1634. For being ſent for to a yong gentleman whoſe name was <hi>Arthur Buckeridge</hi> ſon unto M. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Buckeridge</hi> now of
<hi>Tottenham</hi> Gentleman, who was ſick of that kind of pox which our Country people call the Flocks, which were many, flat headed, white, and wrought along, as if wormes had made certaine crooked fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes among them, which when at firſt I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, I was very diffident in my ſelfe of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any cure, becauſe I never-knew any of that diſeaſe and manner ſaved: Yet while the friends of the Youth declared unto mee what an ingenious child and ſcholler he was, and what hopes all his friends had of him: I ſtill beheld the variegation, or vermiculation of that kind of <hi>variolae:</hi> And becauſe no Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian in all my reading ever gave me the leaſt light or helpe to cure them: J more ſtudiouſly ſearching the cauſe of their forme, ſtrongly apprehended that that outward work and waving could proceed from no cauſe, but from putrefaction cauſed of worms; and that God and nature did aſſiſt in ſo great a difficulty, ſhewing by this external ſignature the internall cauſe, taking therefore my <hi>Indicative</hi> from the <hi>Conjunctive</hi> (as <hi>Galen</hi> counſelleth very well) J preſcribed chiefly againſt wormes and inward putrefaction, and in very ſhort ſpace he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to his health: And while I write theſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12788:18"/>things, the yong-man (whom J never ſaw ſince) commeth in to my houſe to ſearch after me, and to give me thanks ſo long after, being ſhortly to goe for <hi>Oxford:</hi> Wherefore to confirme this Hiſtory I ſent unto the Young-mans Apothecary to ſee what was yet upon file, to aſcertaine what I ſay; and it is retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me, that two of my bils are yet there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining: As alſo one honeſt Gentleman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth well that I then expreſſed as much and told his friends that I intended to preſcribe againſt the worms principally.</p>
            <p>The other Hiſtory was of this <hi>Iohn Pennant,</hi> whom we diſſected; who was well known unto me, as his friends and others well can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it, in whom as is likewiſe ſufficiently knowne, I very often noted this, that he had an excellent Eye, but extraordinarily ſharpe, and like the Eye of a Serpent, and ſo much I have ſpoken of it, that divers Gentlemen and good Schollers did make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer unto me that heard of his long diſeaſes of the ſuppoſed ſtone, or ulcer of the bladder: that pains and griefes did ſharpen mens aſpects: But finding what we have ſeene in him, thus much ſhall mine owne obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion teach me ever; Let others doe, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as little as they pleaſe, that <hi>ſecret, unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall and strange inward diſeaſes, doe ſend forth ſome radios, or ſignatures from the center, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogicall to the circumference, by which we may finde the cauſes if we be diligent and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full:</hi> 
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12788:18"/>And this is that which I would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, of which I know no man that hath written one word as yet: Which although at firſt it ſeemeth new, yet if men will well conſider it and what I ſhall ſay I doubt not but they will be confirmed, that it is an accurate and a moſt neceſſary obſervation, and a chiefe Window to ſee into the moſt ſecret di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes and Cloſets of the body and heart alſo.</p>
            <p>And firſt as an introduction to beliefe what helps Phyſitians may have from beames and ſignatures. All learned Phyſitians will thus farre goe vvith me, that this vvas that admirable way of the old <hi>Magitians</hi> to find out the natures of medicines, from their peculiar beams, ſignatures and ſimilitudes, and that there is no Simple or medicine <hi>Specifical</hi> (as they ſay) or excellent for any diſeaſe or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few, but we are able to make the <hi>radij</hi> or ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natures to appeare, from which thoſe learned <hi>Magi</hi> did, or might find out the properties and virtues of thoſe Simples or medicines, and this you know to be true, and this way you all know that <hi>Sponſa Solis</hi> or the <hi>Kiramides</hi> of the
<hi>Synas</hi> went, as that book of the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> ſheweth, which I lent unto you; and you have no doubt many volumes of Phyſitians as well as others who have written of this argument. Wherefore ſeeing it is ſo cleare that ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and beames have ſo excellently and clearely diſcovered the virtues of all medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines <pb n="28" facs="tcp:12788:19"/>latent and abſtruſe. Shall we conceive that God and Nature are deficient in affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding outwardly ſome helps to know the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſecret and ſtrangeſt maladies? It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be: For to what purpoſe is it, that the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples have virtues medicinall, and for every diſeaſe, if ſome diſeaſes may not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and how can they bee diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered within, to which no eye can come? from which nothing is received, as in ſome other diſeaſes. Some are knowne by time, as Feavers, keeping Period: Some by place or part affected, as <hi>Cholick, Angine,</hi> Stone in the reynes, and the like. Some by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions, as Diſſenteries. Some by ſuch like and others more or leſſe: But there is no meanes to diſcover ſuch a thing as this that hath given occaſion of all this diſcourſe, for nothing was excerned of it any waies, or from it that could give any light: No topicall griefe ſo great as that in his reynes and bladder, he did complaine of his breaſt and of a beating there ſometimes; but <hi>Palpitatio cordis</hi> is <hi>ſignum commune.</hi> Neither did this man complaine as he did alwaies of his other affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Neither can it be imagined how ſuch a ſubſtance growing and receiving daily aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation in his heart could be diſcovered by the wit of man, but by ſome outward thing ſingular and unuſuall, as a ſpeciall
<hi>radius</hi> of what was within.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:12788:19"/>
            <head>§. 8.</head>
            <p>I truſt then that this ſpeculation and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe will in time be thought of, and that it may, I will ſet this ſignature upon it (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſeldome or ſcarce ever noted by any except by Friar
<hi>Bacon</hi> in his Booke <hi>de Caelo &amp; mundo,</hi> &amp;c. More eſpecially by that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable ſage <hi>Alkinaus,</hi> the moſt learned man that the Eaſt ſince his time, or long before hath brought forth unto the world: that every thing hath his <hi>radios proprios,</hi> as well as the ſtarres of Heaven have: <hi>Alkindus</hi> his wordes are theſe, in his Treatiſe <hi>de radijs,</hi> as a firme concluſion, and ſufficiently there by him confirmed; <hi>Agite ergo cum mundus Elementaris ſit exemplum mundi, it a quod quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet res in ipſo contenta ipſius ſpeciem continet. Manifeſtum eſt quod omnis res huj us mundt ſive ſit ſubſtantia, ſive accidens, radios facit ſuo modo ad instar ſiderum, alioquin figuram mundi ſyderci ad plenum non haberet.</hi> But this we will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the ſenſe in ſome few (ſaith hee) the fire tranſmitteth his beames to a certaine diſtance: the earth ſends out her beames of colde, of medicine, and of health; and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines taken into the body, or outwardly applied, diffuſe their beames through the wholebody of him that receives them: the colliſion of ſolid bodies makes a ſound which diffuſeth it ſelfe by the beames of the thing <pb n="30" facs="tcp:12788:20"/>moved: and every coloured body ſendeth out his beames, by which it is perceived, and this is ſubtely knowne in moſt other things: by which by <hi>vive</hi> reaſon it is certainely knowne to be true in all things; taking this therefore for truth wee ſay, that every thing which hath actuall exiſtence in the elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary world, ſendes forth his beames, which fill the elementary world after their manner, whereupon every place of this world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth the beames of all things which are actually exiſtent in every place: And as every thing differeth from other; ſo the beames of every thing do differ in effect and nature from the beames of all other things, by which it comes to paſſe that the operation of the beames is diverſe in all diverſe things: Thus farre, and much more <hi>Alkindus</hi> to the ſame and like effect: Yet I will ad ſome few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances more. The ſeverall ſmelles of all things in the world, are their ſeverall <hi>radij</hi> which doe diſcover themſelves unto us, and we perceive them to be many times where we ſee them not: Wee ſmell Roſes, Musk, Civit, Amber, Quinces, Apples, Plantes and herbes of all ſortes, and very many other thinges in roomes or boxes, before we come neere them: and we are moſt times aſſured of ſuch things to be neere us, by their proper and peculiar emanations, or irradiations, which are their ſpecifick beames, darting out and diffuſing themſelves from one cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12788:20"/>unto a certaine diſtance, according to the vertue of the ſpecies or his proper nature, which may doubtleſſe alſo be intended, or remitted, or varied, and ſo make ſtrong pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, according to the rectitude of line, or elſe be debilitated according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of obliquation: but this I inſiſt not upon.</p>
            <p>Fetted things alſo have their <hi>radios,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their owne proper nature, and there is the ſame reaſon of them in all points accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſpecies: The colours of other things are alſo beames: and the very truth is, that as all thinges in the world have their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<hi>radios:</hi> ſo all the actions that they have is by vertue of theſe
<hi>radij:</hi> and as <hi>Alkindus</hi> ſaith, by theſe beames is exerciſed <hi>in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctum localiter, aut in ſeperatum:</hi> which the Schoole-men call <hi>immediatio virtutis,</hi> or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatio ſuppoſiti:</hi> in both, nothing is done <hi>ſine radijs,</hi> nor truly knowne: As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, If two men come cloſe together, one cannot ſtrike another, <hi>Immediatione ſuppoſiti,</hi> except the <hi>animales radij</hi> actuate the nerves and muſcles of the hand, and therefore
<hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatio virtutis</hi> is ſuppoſed. Theſe ſpirits are the
<hi>radij animales,</hi> and by theſe every action arbitrary or not arbitrary is effected in or by man, and every other creature.</p>
            <p>And as cleare to us is that action which is performed
<hi>immediatione virtutis</hi> in other creatures; for we ſee an Adamant to draw <pb n="32" facs="tcp:12788:21"/>yron at a diſtance: A looking Glaſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Images of things ſeparated from the glaſſe: And this we know muſt bee by ſome Emiſſion or projection of beames one towards another, as well as by the Emiſſion of the animall ſpirits from the braine into the nerves. And a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous wonder it hath beene to me to ſee how Mineralls purified and defecated from <hi>heterogeniall</hi> mixtures, finding themſelves free doe ſtrike out themſelves in any liquour into branches and Starrs, as is acknowledged by Phyſitians, calling them
<hi>medicinas ſtell at as,</hi> as <hi>Mercurius Stellatus: Regulas Antimonij Stellatas,</hi> &amp;c. and not onely <hi>Minerals</hi> doe thus, but the Salt of vegetables, and animals I have made ſo, that they will doe the like: So that it is evident that every thing in the world hath his beames; and it cannot, nor ought not to be otherwiſe, ſith the nine times moſt bleſſed and moſt glorious Eſſentator of all things who hath beene ſo diffuſive, as to branch out himſelfe into every thing viſible and inviſible, that any thing ſhould not have ſome likeneſſe unto him who made all things <hi>ſummaratione,</hi> and with as great perfections as their ſeverall ſpecies were capable of. And for them therefore not to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and who was their Father, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Coelum est in terra ſed modo terreſtri:</l>
               <l>Terra eſt in Coelo, ſed modo Coeleſti:</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:12788:21"/>Yea even putrid humours, and materiall cauſes of diſeaſes, as being naturall things though corrupted are good: and have their beames and their ſignatures in ſavours, puſtles, bubos, ſpots, and tokens without, of divers ſorts according to the ſeverall ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the humour putrified within, or from the commixtion with other cauſes by which a Phyſitian is much inſtructed, what is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and how to take heed himſelfe; and to come home to the very point, and cauſe of all this Diſcourſe, we ſee in all kind of Animals in the world (and I doubt not but your incredible deſire to know and excellent naturall ſagacity hath often obſerved) that according as their arteriall blood is exalted, ſuch
<hi>radij</hi> are in their Eyes; as we ſee in ſome men more then others, and in Cocks, and in Serpents: A Cocke hath an Eye whoſe <hi>radij</hi> are almoſt exalted to the beames of the Eye of a Serpent: And doubtleſſe ſuch blood had this man, and ſuch ſpirits of an incredible heate or acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony: The Eye is an <hi>Index animi,</hi> which cannot otherwiſe be then by the <hi>radij</hi> or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of it, much more then doth it ſhew the blood arteriall upon which thoſe ſpirits are founded; and thus from the Eye I have made it evident, that we may know much of the left Ventricle of the heart where the arteriall bloud is elaborated and made: And thus in other matters, if from the <hi>radij</hi> or ſignatures <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12788:22"/>exterior we play the good <hi>Magitians</hi> and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently conſider them: I am perſwaded wee may have a ſingular helpe and inſight to cure the moſt hidden and moſt dangerous diſeaſes of all, and ſuch as otherwiſe cannot be known. You ſee Sir, I have founded my ſentence upon God, Nature, and Experience, and if it be hidden or not believed by any, it is to them incredible who have groſſe conceptions, ſmall skill, as J am ſure your great inſight and wiſdome will and can better confirme: For what is that which makes ſome men wiſer then others? <hi>Magis ſapiens eſt &amp; dicitur qui minus perceptibilia percipit de rebus &amp; earum conditionibus,</hi> ſaith that wiſe man <hi>Alkindus:</hi> There is no doubt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as the ſame man ſaith) but that they who are informed with an holy deſire of wiſedome will labour much to comprehend the ſecret conditions of things, as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Phyſitians did who with wonderfull ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacity ſearched for that skill which we injoy: As for ſuch as are neither wiſe nor have deſire of wiſedome, I leave them to
<hi>Ptolemey</hi> that other miracle of knowledge to inſtruct the world of them; <hi>Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt inſipientes quod non comprehendunt,</hi> unwiſe men reprehend all that they doe not comprehend.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="section">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:12788:22"/>
            <head>§. 9.</head>
            <p>IT remaines onely that ſomething be ſaid of the cure of ſuch Conceptions if by any Phyſitian they be perceived in time: Either by pulſation of the heart or by any externall ſigne or ſignature, or
<hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſome who uſe no alterants nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther peice of art then to kill and diſſolve ſuch conceptions: and they confide in this. ℞.
<hi>Succi Allij, Naſturtij, Raphani, ana.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>.j. <hi>detur &amp; ſtatim curabitur.</hi> So <hi>Schenckins</hi> from <hi>Stockerus.</hi> Others thus. ℞. <hi>Tanaceti ramulum in umbra ſiccatum, in pulverem redactum cribella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, cui addatur pulvis ſequens,</hi> ℞. <hi>Rad gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian. Rad. Paeoniae longae, ana.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>.j. <hi>Myrrhae,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>.ſs.
<hi>miſce, tere &amp; cum uti volueris.</hi> ℞. ℈.j. <hi>Et cum guttula aquae ut ſolum madefiat miſce, deinde inunge os &amp; lahra infantis aut patientis ter aut quater, &amp; una cum caeteris medicamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis eijcientur.</hi> So <hi>Schenckins.</hi> This I grant is good for wormes that cauſe <hi>Epileptike</hi> fits in children, but for ſuch as lie deeper in the <hi>pericardium</hi> and the left Ventricle, it is not likely they will be ſenſible of, at ſo great a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and incloſure: I rather thinke that the uſe of ſome oyles which are more penetrative, may do more good, as ſome drops of <hi>Olei de Sabina in aqua juventutis, Raimundi</hi> or
<hi>Olei ex Baccis Iuniperi ob ejus penetrativam virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:12788:23"/>may with ſome continuance or with the ſucceſſe before mentioned be more effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious: But why am I ſo large ſpeaking to you? But to lay ſome grounds of future diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes with you, concerning both preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and cure of ſuch latent maladies, rather then here to ſet them out.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="section">
            <head>§. 10.</head>
            <p>Yet for concluſion I have onely this one thing to note unto the world: how that theſe which ſeeme ſo rare, ſtrange, and incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable miſchiefes, might be more familiarly knowne, and eaſily cured, if it were not for a babiſh, or a kinde of cockney diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our common people, who think their children or friendes murdered after they are dead, if a Surgion ſhould but pierce any part of their skinnes with a knife: by which it commeth to paſſe, that few of thoſe innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable and marvellous conceptions, which kill the parents in which they are bred, (as your ſelfe with admiration have knowingly ſpoken to me of their infinite number which are generated in mans body) can ever be found out, or cured: ſo great a monſter is begotten in the blood of fooles, and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people, which deſtroyeth the common good of man-kinde in a very great propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: whereas that knowledge of their generations, which Phyſitions have, is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12788:23"/>commonly from the diſſections of the bodies of Noble Perſonages, and of the Gentry, who with their friendes about them have beene bred to more fortitude, and are more wiſe and communicative, as moſt of our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinall hiſtories, you know confirme, and your ſelfe likewiſe hath told me of ſome. All vertuous and heroick ſoules know that when their particle of divine perfection is returned to him that gave it, that then their bodies are to ſerve the univerſe (as that pious Biſhop knew) who when he had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven away all beſides his body, at laſt gave that alſo for the good of the living, when it ſhould be found dead, and therefore bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed it to the Phyſitians to diſſect it: but doubtleſſe our Tradeſmen, their wives and children, and our ſugar-ſop citizens are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of a rarer,
<hi>noli me tangere,</hi> when they are dead then when they were alive; And though Nobles and Princes may be cut in peeces, yet is it <hi>piacular,</hi> and the loſſe of grace for ever with them, if a Phiſitian ſhould but intimate ſuch a matter as decently but to open any part of their moſt intemerate Impes.</p>
            <p>But what good more frequent diſſections might doe, what portentuous matters they might diſcover, and how facile they might finde the cauſes, and their cure, you ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently know, and in part others may by this hiſtory underſtand: And although the <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12788:24"/>learning and knowledge of ſome Phiſitions of our age be ſingular, and growne to ſuch an happy degree of perfection, yet there are by diſſections every day ſomething to be learned: and how much the internall do ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolize with externall, as in part I have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and J will yet give out one il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration more: let but Phiſitions well note their patients complections, and colours (for this time I will onely ſpeake of the face) and let them take afterward if they come to diſſect them notice of their livers, and if they be diligent, in few diſſections they ſhall be able, looking into any mans face what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, to know the affections very manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his liver. Sir, under favour, and with you J have thus much freedome as to tell ſome of my brother Phiſitions and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, that the inſpections and diſſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which they celebrate over the world, are not to inable men to talke of names, parts and places, but to doe, and to be able to judge of thinges hidden and ſecret, that they may not be deceived tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the cauſes of mens diſeaſes: this is the chiefeſt end, and yet how few ſtudy out of entrailes this learning, I neede not intimate unto you.</p>
            <p>The wayes of nature, by which opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are effected, as alſo the continuation of parts and veſſels, their communication, and to finde the cauſes of ſickneſſes, their epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneſes, <pb n="39" facs="tcp:12788:24"/>their metaſtaſes, their apoſtaſes, their
<hi>palyndromyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The wayes of Simptomes, reaſons of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions and the like, are the next: and ſo much ſubordinate to the other, and of leſſe neceſſity, as obuious inſpections ſhewe this to be more facile, and with leſſe labour to be attained then that; the other therefore not being ſo well perfected to our dayes, I have by this extraordinary occaſion, and out of my good wiſhes, ventured to ſpeake a word by you, unto ſuch as are wiſe in our owne profeſſion, ſince Phiſitians ſhould be
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as our dictators word is,
<hi>like Gods,</hi> what is in us in good skill, and good will, for the ſafety of man-kinde: that as it was ſaid of his dayes, ſo it may of ours,
<hi>in corum diebu; raro animae deſcendebant ad infernum:</hi> in their dayes, ſoules ſeldome deſcended into hell, if any at laſt forſaking divine grace ſhall deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend; yet that hell may gape a long time ere it receive them, and that others may have time to ſhake handes with Heaven, that our profeſſion, the nobleſt and wiſeſt of all others, (I ſpeake of profeſſions which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne this life onely, not of profeſſions ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall) may ſtill be eſteemed divineſt (as the old Phiſitians were crowned deſervedly, and related among the Gods, above all others) while by our meanes, miſerable men are reſtored to the onely bleſſing of this life, health; and (as I ſaid) be preſerved <pb n="40" facs="tcp:12788:25"/>from that great and eternall gulph of infelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Hell (many of them not being in ſtate of grace, becauſe ſicke upon their ſinnes) and laſtly, made live till they be friends and ſonnes of God, and ſo rich as to come to Heaven: our Saviour Chriſt crowning us with ſuch happy mindes, as to be made inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and meanes of many mens eternall ſalvation, by occaſion of their temporall reſtitution.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12788:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
